Guide to the German broadsides collection, 1870-1990 and undated, bulk 1920s RL.00444
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
German broadsides collection
1870-1990 and undated, bulk 1920s
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.00444
5.8 Linear Feet Approximately 519 items
The German broadsides collection spans the years 1870-1990, with the majority of items dating from the 1920s. Broadsides (single-sided announcements and texts) predominate, but there are also several diplomas, leaflets, handbills, campaign publications, political brochures, propaganda posters, and other ephemera documenting the political, economic, and social conditions in Germany, Eastern Europe, Russia, and China, particularly during the Weimar Republic. Many of the broadsides relate to elections during the 1920s and the legacy of World War I as well as the political implications of women's suffrage during that time. Political parties represented include the Socialist Party, the Communist Party, the German Democratic Party, and the German National People's Party, as well as several smaller parties. The majority come from cities across Germany, with Leipzig and Berlin strongly represented. Additional materials include Allied propaganda leaflets and Holocaust exhibition posters, as well as materials relating to the assassination of German Foreign Minister Walther Rathenau in 1922, and several diplomas, 1870-1924 relating to the Von Baudissin family. Closely related to the German Newspaper Clippings Collection.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The German Broadsides Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 1948.
Collection Overview
The German Broadsides Collection spans the years 1870-1990, with the majority of items dating from the 1920s. Broadsides predominate, but there are also leaflets, handbills, campaign publications, political brochures, propaganda posters, and other ephemera documenting the political, economic, and social conditions in early 20th century Germany, Eastern Europe, Russia, and China. Many of these items contain political cartoons and caricatures. Sizes vary greatly, from small leaflets 3x5 inches, to large posters 28x32 inches in size.
The collection provides rich documentation on the political climate in early twentieth-century Germany, in a variety of cities, but especially Leipzig and Berlin, and within a variety of political parties. The bulk of this material was produced in the years from 1919-1924 and from 1928-1930, both periods of political and economic instability. In the Weimar Republic, 1913-1933, numerous political parties vied for German votes and materials in the collection document this competition. With the extension of suffrage to German women in 1919, political parties (especially the Socialist Party) began to tailor their election propaganda towards these new voters, as is reflected in numerous broadsides in this collection. Of note in the collection are two Käthe Kollwitz drawings, and the Reichsbund jüdischer Frontsoldaten broadside An die deutschen Mütter.
The majority of the political pieces were disseminated by the Socialist Party, the Communist Party, the German Democratic Party, and the German National People's Party, with some material from the Center Party and from Richard Kunze's anti-Semitic German Social Party.
The elections broadsides along with other political ephemera chiefly relate to the 1919 National Assembly election and the 1920 and 1924 Reichstag elections; these are arranged according to election, and within each election according to city. Broadly speaking, they address economic, political, and cultural themes debated in national, state, and local elections in the 1920s in Germany, as well as the legacy of the First World War.
Additional materials include several diplomas, 1870-1924, from the Universities of Berlin and Leipzig, relating to the Von Baudissin family; two sets of Holocaust exhibition posters produced in the late twentieth-century by the Anti-Defamation League and the United States Holocaust Memorial Council; and posters relating to commemorations of the assassination of German Foreign Minister Walther Rathenau in 1922, the political situation in China, Poland, and Russia, among others, and international peace, workers, and anti-imperialism movements. The collection also includes three unaddressed letters from the Zentralkomitee Internationale Arbeiterhilfe about events in Hungary and China.
Closely related to the German Newspaper Clippings Collection.
Collection Arrangement
Organized into the following series: German Diplomas, Allied Propaganda Leaflets; Campaign Publications and Political Brochures; Elections; Holocaust Exhibition Posters; International Relations and Movements; Walther Rathenau Assassination; and Other Items.
Separated Material
The following items have been separated and relocated to the Currency Collection and the Postcard Collection: a piece of German currency (10 million Reichsmarks) from 1923, and a letter from Chicago to Leipzig with a fold-out accordion sheet of 19 labeled postcards of a parade/community event in the United States.
Related Material
German newspapers in the Rubenstein Library
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
German Newspaper Clippings Collection
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
World War II Propaganda Leaflets, 1941-1945
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Fliers (printed matter); Germany -- Politics and government -- 1918-1933; Brochures; Broadsides (notices); Antisemitism -- Germany; Elections -- Germany -- 1920-1940; Holocaust, Jewish (1939-1945); Holocaust memorials; Propaganda, Communist -- Germany; Nazi propaganda -- Germany; World politics -- Caricatures and cartoons; World War, 1914-1918; Berlin (Germany) -- History; Leipzig (Germany) -- History; Germany -- History -- 1918-1933; Handbills; Political posters; Deutsche Zentrumspartei; Deutschnationale Volkspartei; Deutsche Demokratische Partei; Nationalsozialistische Deutsche Arbeiter-Partei; Rathenau, Walther,1867-1922 -- Assassination; Kommunistische Partei Deutschlands; Sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands
- German Diplomas, 1870-1924
  - Diploma [Doctorate in Theology?] belonging to Wolf Wilhelm von Baudissin, 1880 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Diplomas and other large document related to Von Baudissin family, University of Leipzig and Berlin, 4 items (Oversize-folder 2)
    Scope and Contents
    Oversize diplomas and other official document belonging to Wolf Wilhelm Friedrich Graf von Baudissin (1847-1926), German Protestant theologian, professor, and scholar of Semitic and biblical studies at the University of Berlin, and his son, Wolf Graf Von Baudissin (1907-1993), German military planner and architect of the modern German Bundeswehr, University of Leipzig.
- Allied Propaganda Leaflets, 1944 and undated, 1 box
  Scope and Contents note
  Small leaflets produced by the Allied powers and distributed in Germany and Italy as propaganda targeting Axis military forces and civilian populations.
  - Im Osten [...] Im Westen, 1944 (2 copies) (Box 1)
  - Safe Conduct, (2 copies) (Box 1)
  - Achtung! Minen! (Box 1)
  - Wer wird Deutschland wieder aufbauen? (Box 1)
  - Safe-Conduct (21st Army Group) (Box 1)
  - Perché Morire Per Hitler? (Box 1)
  - Le général Eisenhower s'adresse au peuples des Pays Occupés (Box 1)
- Campaign Publications and Political Brochures, 1919-1924, 2 boxes and 1 oversize folder
  Contains broadsides, leaflets, and handbills relating to local, state, and national elections, mostly from the Socialist Party and the German Democratic Party, with some material from other interest groups. They originated from German newspapers and election newspapers printed and distributed by political parties. Arranged chronologically.
  - Flugschriften der Deutschen Demokratischen Partei. Staat und Kirche (Leipzig, circa 1919) (Box 1)
  - Leitsätze der Deutschen Demokratischen Partei für Leipzig und Umgegend (Leipzig, 1919) (Box 1)
  - Wahlaufruf der Deutschen Demokratischen Partei (Leipzig, 1919) (Box 1)
  - Soll die evangelische Schule religionslos werden? (Berlin, 1919) (Box 1)
  - Was sind wir unserer evangelischen Kirche schuldig? (Berlin, 1919) (Box 1)
  - Ein Bekenntnis zu Demokratie, Republik und Volksgemeinschaft (German Democratic Party, 1924) (Box 1)
  - Die Amerikafahrt des L.Z. 126, ein Erfolg demokratischer Politik! (German Democratic Party, Stuttgart, 1924) (Box 3)
  - Raus die Gefangenen!, newspaper format (Socialist Party, Berlin, 1924) (Oversize-folder 2)
  - Arbeitskolleginnen und Arbeitskollegen! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
  - In das amtliche Wahlkuvert muß der mit gleichen Aufdruck versehene Stimmezettel gesteckt werden (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
- Elections, 1919-1933 and undated, 4 boxes and 1 oversize folder
  The largest group in the collection. Contains electioneering broadsides targeting the general population, political party members, and interest groups such as women, blue- and white-collar workers, Catholics, students, and farmers. The broadsides are predominantly small leaflets printed with political slogans and party platforms, announcements of rallies, and instructions to voters either on one or both sides. Arranged according to election, then by city, then by political party.
  - 1919 National Assembly Elections Subseries
    - Berlin, 2 folders
      - Center Party
        - Deutsche Frauen! (Center Party) (Box 1)
      - German Democratic Party
        - Auf zur Wahl! Wähler, Wählerinnen! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - An die Hausfrauen! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - Die ausschlaggebende Partei (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - Deutsche Männer und Frauen! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - Naumann/Freier Staat und freie Kirche (Ein Wort an deutsche Männer und Frauen) (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - Für den Wahltag. Wählerinnen! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - Kirchenglocken im neuen Deutschland (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - Wähler und Wäherlinnen! Euer Tag ist gekommen! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
      - German National People's Party
        - Aufruf! (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
        - An die Berliner Wählerinnen (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Deutsche Frauen--Deutsche Treue! (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Deutsche Männer, deutsche Frauen! (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Deutsche Volk wache auf! (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Staats- und Gemeinde-Beamten, Beamtinnen und Angestellte! (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Wahlaufruf der Deutschnationalen Volkspartei (German National People's Party, 2 copies) (Box 1)
        - Werte Mitbürger! Wähler-Versammlung am Montag, den 13. Januar (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
      - German People's Party
        - An Alle! (German People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Die 14 Punkte. Was will die Deutsche Volkspartei? (German People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Versammlungen der Deutschen Volkspartei (German People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Versammlung der Deutschen Volkspartei (German People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Was hat die Revolution gebracht? (German People's Party) (Box 1)
      - Independent Socialist Party of Germany
        - Wähler und Wäherlinnen! Wählt am 19. Januar die Liste der Unabhängigen sozialdemokrat. Partei Deutschlands (Box 1)
      - Socialist Party
        - Masken herunter! Zeigt, wer Ihr seid-- (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
        - Die Strömungen im Sozialismus (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
      - Other
        - An die Wähler und Wählerinnen zur Nationalversammlung! (Bund deutscher Bodenreformer) (Box 1)
        - An die deutschen Wählerinnen! (Box 1)
        - Der evangelische Christ und die Nationalversammlung (Box 1)
        - Die evangelische Frau und die Not der Zeit (Box 1)
        - Frauen: der Tag ist da! (Box 1)
        - Frauen-Merkblatt für die Wahl zur National-Versammlung (Box 1)
        - Für unsere Kirche! (Evangelische Preßverband für Deutschland) (Box 1)
        - Merkblatt für die kommenden Wahlen zur Nationalversammlung (Berliner Verband Ev. Arbeiter- und Arbeiterinnenvereine) (Box 1)
        - Die Wahlen zur Nationalversammlung stehen hervor! Sie sollen und wollen wählen! (Verband Evangel. Arbeiter- und Arbeiterinnen-Vereine) (Box 1)
        - Deutsche Männer! Deutsche Frauen! Nieder mit allen zerstörenden Kräften! (Nationaldemokratische Partei Deutschlands) (Box 1)
        - Wie wähle ich? Bürger und Bauer! Frauen und Jungfrauen! […] Die Sozialdemokratie kann es nicht sein (Oversize-box 1)
  - 1919 National Assembly Elections Subseries (cont.)
    - Berlin-Charlottenburg
      - Einladung zur Oeffentlichen Versammlung (German Democratic Party) (Box 3)
      - An die Wählerinnen des Wahlkreises Teltow, Beeskow-Storkow, Charlottenburg (German National People's Party) (Box 3)
    - Berlin-Moabit
      - Männer und Frauen von Moabit! Der Tag der Entscheidung naht! Deutschland ist in höchster Not! Auf zur Tat! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
    - Braunschweig
      - An das deutsche Volk! (German Democratic Party) (Box 3)
      - An die deutschen Frauen! (German Democratic Party) (Box 3)
      - An die Männer und Frauen des Landes Braunschweig! (German Democratic Party (Demokratische Volkspartei)) (Box 3)
    - Bremen
      - Frauen und Mädchen! (Independent Socialist Party of Germany) (Box 1)
    - Dresden
      - Christliche Männer und Frauen! (Center Party) (Box 1)
      - An alle Handwerker Sachsens! (Landesausschuß des Sächsischen Handwerks) (Box 1)
    - Königsberg
      - Staats- und Gemeindebeamten, Beamtinnen und Angestellte! (German National People's Party) (Box 3)
      - Staats- und Kommunal-Beamte (German National People's Party) (Box 3)
      - Aufruf. Deutschnational Volkspartei (German National People's Party) (Box 3)
    - Leipzig
      - Communist Party
        - Warum habt ihr gestreikt? (Communist Party) (Box 1)
      - Independent Socialist Party of Germany
        - Arbeiter! Bürger! Bauern! (Independent Socialist Party of Germany) (Box 1)
        - Wähler, Wählerinnen, überlegt, wen ihr wählt? (Independent Socialist Party of Germany) (Box 1)
      - Other
        - Frauen als Wählerinnen! Wie muß ich wählen? (Werbeausschuß für politische Betätigung der Frauen) (Box 1)
        - Hört deutsche Frauen! Ihr deutschen Frauen hört! (Werbeausschuß für politische Betätigung der Frauen) (Box 1)
        - Frauen und Mütter!....Friede auf Erden! (Box 1)
        - Zum 19. Januar! (Box 1)
    - Place Unknown
      - Deutschnationale Kundgebung (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
  - 1920 Reichstag Elections Subseries
    - Berlin
      - German Democratic Party
        - An die deutsche Studentenschaft! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - An alle Beamte im Reichs-, Staats- und Gemeindedienst! Beamte, Lehrer, Angestellte! Männer und Frauen! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - Die Deutsche Demokratische Partei eine Partei des sozialen Ausgleichs (Box 1)
        - Deutsche Arbeiter und deutsche Arbeiterinnen! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
      - German National People's Party
        - Achtung!--Das Wahlproblem! Wen wählst Du? (German National People's Party, 2 copies) (Box 1)
        - Deutsche Katholiken! (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Deutschnationale Volkspartei. Für ehrliche Arbeit, Recht und Ordnung! Gegen Schieber- und Schmarotzertum! (Box 1)
        - Der Dolchstoß von hinten (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Demokraten oder Bankerotteure? (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Unser Wahlvorschläge (German National People's Party (Box 1)
      - German People's Party
        - Der Auszug der Enttäuschten (German People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Aufruf der Deutschen Volkspartei! (2 copies) (Box 1)
        - Lügen haben kurze Beine! (German People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Die klarblickenden Privatangestellten aus allen Gewerkschaftsgruppen (German People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Wehr dich gewerblicher Mittelstand! (German People's Party) (Box 1)
      - Socialist Party
        - Wacht endlich auf, tretet ein für euer Wohl und euer Recht, Wählt die sozialdemokratische Partei Deutschlands (S.P.D.) (Box 1)
        - Deutsch-Demokratisch oder Sozialdemokratisch? (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
        - Der Feind steht rechts! (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
      - Other
        - Reichstagswählerversammlung (National Democratic People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Weitersagen, Kameraden! (Friedensbund der Kriegsteilnehmer) (Box 1)
        - Der 6. Juni entscheidet über unser nächstes Schicksal! (Oversize-folder 1)
    - Berlin-Charlottenberg
      - Die Gefahr von links!….Die Gefahr von rechts! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
    - Berlin-Moabit
      - Augen links!....Keine Stimme einem Sozialdemokraten! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
    - Berlin-Spandau
      - Das große Rätsel (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
    - Braunschweig
      - Deutsche demokratische Partei. Donnerstag, 3. Juni 1920, abends 8 Uhr Große öffentliche Wähler-Versammlung... (Box 1)
      - Deutsche demokratische Partei, Donnerstag...Große öffentliche Wähler-Versammlung (German Democratic Party) (Oversize-folder 2)
      - Wähler Helfferichs! (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
    - Bremen
      - Communist Party
        - Frauen u. Mädchen des Proletariats! Arbeiterinnen und Angestellte! Hausfrauen u. Mütter! (Communist Party) (Box 1)
        - Männer u. Frauen Bremens! (German People's Party) (Oversize-box 1)
      - German Democratic Party
        - Bremische Wähler und Wählerinnen! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
      - German People's Party
        - Wie wählen wir am 6. Juni zum Reichstag und zur Bremischen Bürgerschaft? (German People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Die 10 Gebote für den Wahltag! (German People's Party) (Box 1)
      - Independent Socialist Party of Germany
        - Öffentl. Wähler-Versammlung (Independent Socialist Party of Germany) (Box 1)
        - Warum?--Weil! (Independent Socialist Party of Germany) (Box 1)
      - Socialist Party
        - Abrechnung mit der Reaktion (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
        - An die bremischen Hand- u. Kopfarbeiter, Angestellten, Beamten, Hausfrauen! (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
        - Ein letztes Wort! (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
        - Oeffentliche Wählerversammlung (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
  - 1920 Reichstag Elections Subseries (cont.)
    - Dresden
      - Deustsche Frauen--Deutsche Treue! (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
      - Der Wahlkampf beginnt! (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
    - Halle
      - German People's Party
        - Deutsche Wähler u. Wählerinnen! (German People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Handwerker, Kaufleute, Gewerbetreibende! Wehrt euch! (German People's Party) (Box 1)
      - Independent Socialist Party of Germany
        - Auf zur Wahlschlacht! Führt den Entscheidungsschlag! (Independent Socialist Party of Germany) (Box 1)
        - Sozialismus oder Kapitalismus? (Independent Socialist Party of Germany) (Box 1)
      - Socialist Party
        - Wähler und Wählerinnen! (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
      - Other
        - Achtung! Achtung! Grosse Gefahr! Deutsche Männer und Frauen, Arbeiter und Bürger! Der 6. Juni ruft zur Wahl! (Box 1)
    - Hannover
      - Die Entscheidung naht! (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
    - Leipzig
      - German Democratic Party
        - Antwort auf die Reden in der Versammlung der Deutschen Demokratischen Partei zu Leipzig am 14. Mai 1920 (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - Erst wäget, dann wählet! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - Oeffentliche Wählerversammlungen (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - Taten, nicht Worte! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
      - German National People's Party
        - Deutschnationaler Opfertag am 16. Mai 1920 (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
      - German People's Party
        - Wählerinnen! Wähler! (German People's Party) (Box 1)
      - Independent Socialist Party of Germany
        - Verbrecher am deutschen Volke (Independent Socialist Party of Germany) (Box 1)
        - Wähler in Stadt und Land, Männer und Frauen! (Independent Socialist Party of Germany) (Box 1)
      - Socialist Party
        - Frauen! Mädchen! Wählerinnen der deutschen Republik [...] Hoch die Sozialdemokratie, die Erlöserin der Frau! (Box 1)
        - Hie Sozialismus, hie Kapitalismus! (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
        - Nach den Reichstagswahlen! (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
        - Wähler und Wählerinnen! (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
      - Other
        - Bürger, Bürgerin wahr' Dir Dein Recht….Bürger, Bürgerin, tu' Deine Pflicht! (Box 1)
    - Merseburg
      - Wahlaufruf der Deutschen demokratische Partei (German Democratic Party) (Oversize-box 1)
    - Mölbis
      - Einwohner von Espenhain, Mölbis und Umgegend! Oeffentliche Wählerversammlung (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
    - Munich
      - Bayerisches Volk! Wach auf! (Bayerische Mittelpartei (German National People's Party)) (Box 1)
      - Bayerisches Volk! Wach auf! (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
      - Frauen des Volkes! (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
    - Zahna
      - Beamte und Beamtinnen! (German People's Party) (Box 1)
    - Place Unknown
      - Communist Party
        - Denkt an Liebknecht! Wählt Spartakus! (Box 1)
        - Arbeiter! Genossen! Keine Stimme den verräterischen Mehrheitsleuten (Communist Party) (Box 1)
        - Das Parlament soll keine Schwatzbude sein, sondern ein Tribunal! Wählt deshalb Kommunisten! (Box 1)
        - Im Parlament gegen das Parlament! Wählt Kommunisten! (Box 1)
        - An die deutschen Wähler! (Communist Party) (Box 1)
        - Warum nicht S.P.D.? Warum nicht U.S.P.? Warum Kommunist? (Box 1)
      - German Democratic Party
        - Die Deutsche Volkspartei ohne Maske! (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - Was verdankt das deutsche Volk den Politikern der Rechtsparteien, der Deutschnationalen und der Deutschen Volkspartei? (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - Schwankende Gestalten (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
        - Beamte, Beamtinnen, Hilfsbeamte, Anwärter, Lehrer, Lehrerinnen und Pensionäre. (German Democratic Party) (Box 1)
      - German National People's Party
        - Wer frei sein will von fremder Zwangsherrschaft… (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
        - Eure jetzige Führer! Wollt Ihr Andere? Dann wählt deutschnational! (German National People's Party) (Box 1)
      - German People's Party
        - Deutsche Volkspartei, die Partei des Wiederaufbaues (Box 1)
      - Socialist Party
        - Beamte! Nie wieder das alte Joch! Wählt sozialdemokratisch! (S.P.D.) (Box 1)
        - Willst du in bessere Zukunft schauen, Und schöpfen wieder neu Vertrauen... (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
        - Militarismus und Junkertum im Bunde mit der Schwerindustrie (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
        - Frauen! Dass Ihr wählen dürft, dankt Ihr der Sozialdemokratie! Darum: Wählt sozialdemokratisch! (Box 1)
        - Wollt ihr einen neuen Krieg, neue Tote, neue Krüppel, neues Elend, so wählt die Parteien der Kriegshetzer (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
        - Wählerinnen und Wähler! Die Gegenrevolution habt Ihr im März niedergeschlagen. (Socialist Party) (Box 1)
      - Other
        - Kameradin! Wie ist es mit der Reichstagswahl am 6. Juni! (Box 1)
        - Fahrt nicht mit der Strassenbahn!.....Bürger! wachtet endlich auf! wenn Ihr nicht Sklaven der Proletarier werden wollt! (Box 1)
  - 1924 Reichstag Elections Subseries
    - Berlin, 3 folders
      - Center Party
        - Auf der ganzen Linie versagt (Center Party) (Box 1)
        - Wähler und Wählerinnen! (Center Party) (Box 1)
        - Werbeplakat (Center Party) (Box 1)
      - Communist Party